<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The second part of the un-deceiver: tending to the discovery of some prelaticall and antinomian errovrs; and the clearing of that part of the late covenant of the three kingdoms which concerns both.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 62KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92828</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859605</idno>
  <idno type="VID">111697</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240889906</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2320</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E72_8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14063</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859605</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99859605e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92828)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 111697)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 12:E72[8])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The second part of the un-deceiver: tending to the discovery of some prelaticall and antinomian errovrs; and the clearing of that part of the late covenant of the three kingdoms which concerns both.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Samuel Gellibrand, at the Brasen-Serpent in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Londnon [sic] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Octob: 26".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="uniform_title">Solemn League and Covenant (1643) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Antinomianism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Susie Lorand </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:111697:1"/>
            <p>The second Part OF THE UN-DECEIVER: Tending to the DISCOVERY Of some <hi>PRELATICALL</hi> AND <hi>ANTINOMIAN</hi> ERROVRS; <hi>AND THE</hi> Clearing of that part of the late COVENANT OF THE THREE KINGDOMS Which concerns Both.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDNON,</hi> Printed for SAMUEL GELLIBRAND, at the Brasen-Serpent in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1643.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:111697:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:111697:2"/>
            <head>THE SECOND PART OF THE Undeceiver: Tending to the Discovery of some <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laticall</hi> and <hi>Antinomian</hi> Errours, and the clearing of that part of the late <hi>Covenant</hi> of the three Kingdomes which concernes both.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are two weighty Points commended to our saddest thoughts in these sad times, namely, how to procure first a Reformation, and then a Pacifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptist was sent in the Spirit of <hi>Elias</hi> to procure both, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.17. to turne the hearts of the Fathers towards the Children, (there's a Pacification) and the disobedient to the wisdome of the just, ther's a Reformation. Now there are two sorts of men that oppose a thorow-Reformation, and therefore hinder a Rationall and Christian Pacification. The first sort are carried away with Prelaticall errours, the second sort are carried away with Antino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mian errours.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:111697:3"/>
            <p>For the first of these, we must consider how they have Idolized the Prelates, and Canonized the Service-book, or (if you will) Canonized the Prelates and Idolized the Service-book.</p>
            <p>First for the Prelates, they are by this time known to be Usur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, and Seducers; now the Rule is, That an <hi>Ancient Ʋsurpation is rather a cause of confusion then a ground for prescription:</hi> It is certaine that the Primitive Church had the best Discipline, and therefore the restoring of the Primitive Discipline cannot be denied to be a Reformation, and <hi>the Reformation of the Church cannot bring desolation upon the State;</hi> because Christ will blesse his own Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and defend his own Discipline by his own power.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But the King hath sworn to maintaine Prelacy, and the Ministers have sworn to yeeld Canonicall obedience.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol.</hi> The Law of Nations frames this Answer, <hi>In omni Iuramento semper excipitur authoritas Majoris.</hi> If you look upon the Church of <hi>England</hi> as a Nationall Church, which hath all the Rights, Priviledges, and Immunities, (which by the Word of God are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred upon every true Church) confirmed unto it and settled upon it by the grand Charter of the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> it is clear and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that neither the King nor the Ministers, can be obliged to give any thing to the Prelates (by vertue of an Oath) which is denied unto the Prelates by Gods Word, (there's <hi>Authoritas Majoris</hi>) and the grand Charter, there's <hi>Authoritas Majorum:</hi> The words of the great Charter are known, yet I will take the paines to tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe them, <hi>Concessimus Deo &amp; hac praefeuti Chartâ confirmavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus pro nobis &amp; haeredibus nostris in perpetium quòd</hi> Ecclesia Angli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cana libera sit; <hi>&amp; habeat omnia jura sua integra &amp; libertates suas illaesas, &amp;c. vide Mag. Chart. c.</hi> 1. This is the Grant of the Kings of <hi>England</hi> which binds them and their Heires for ever, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve all the Rights, Liberties, and Priviledges, (of and in the Church of <hi>England</hi>) which belong to a free Church, and without which a Church cannot bee a free Church. Now the Church of <hi>England</hi> cannot be a free Church, if the Prelates be suffered to Lord it over the Ministers and People of God in <hi>England,</hi> and therefore the King is bound according to the Grand Charter to extirpate Prelacy in <hi>England,</hi> as hee hath already done in <hi>Scotland.</hi> We must bee more carefull of Spirituall then Temporall liberty, we are very tender of the personall liberty of every Subject in particular,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:111697:3"/> but we must be most tender of the liberty of the whole Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of true Protestants as they make one Ecclesiasticall body, or Society, and it doth not lie in the power of any one or more members of that Body, <hi>to sweare away</hi> the liberty of the whole Society or Church, I say Church, for all the sincere Protestants who doe now enter into this Nationall Covenant are a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall Church by vertue of this Covenant; nay, all the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanters in all the three Kingdomes are hereby made one Church, though they cannot in person meet collectively in one Congregation, but in regard of their Multitudes are forced to meet distributively in severall Congregations, or else Represen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatively, in such Guides who are chosen Delegates or Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioners, to propound, reason, or treat in their behalfe in some Generall Assembly; but that by the way.</p>
            <p>We answer farther, if a man have sinned by taking an unlawfull Oath, each Child (that hath learnt his Catechisme) knowes that as soone as hee is convinced of his sinne, he is bound to repent of it, and cannot be engaged in point of conscience to commit a se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond sinne rather then to repent of his former sinne. It would be strange Divinity to affirme that a man is bound in conscience to sinne, and forbid to repent; whether it is better to goe on in a sinne, or repent of a sinne, wee may safely let them judge, <hi>—qui nondum aere lavantur:</hi> Hee that hath sworn rashly, must repent deliberately, and not performe his oath wickedly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he is convinced of the sinfulnesse of his oath; for after convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it is a greater sinne to keep his oath, then it was before conviction to take the oath, because the first was a rash sinne, and a sinne of ignorance and weaknesse, the second is a deliberate sinne against judgement and conscience.</p>
            <p>We need not in these times dispute the point whether the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates be of an <hi>Antichristian Order,</hi> it is sufficient that they are of the <hi>Anti-christian Faction,</hi> for the Prelates in <hi>England</hi> are confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate with the Papists in <hi>England, Ireland;</hi> I might adde <hi>Spaine</hi> and <hi>Italy;</hi> and the Prelates have engaged their owne lives and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, the lives and fortunes of all their Hierarchy (as they call it) from the Deane to the Apparitor, nay, the lives and fortunes of all the Prelaticall party, to promote the blacke and bloody De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signe of the whole <hi>Anti-christian Faction;</hi> so that now we are put
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:111697:4"/> upon these straights, that either we must root out Prelacy, or wee cannot root out Popery, and if we do not root out Popery, the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists will root out Protestantisme, that is, true Christianity; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse then we will lose our Religion, and our Civill right freely to exercise our Religion, unlesse we will go over to the Anti-christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an party, or which is worse, professe Christ, and serve Anti-christ, we are compelled to protest against the Prelaticall Hierarchy, and to endeavour to take away root and branch. Bishop <hi>Hall</hi> made too high a claime, and I beleeve he and his party will repent it. <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops,</hi> saith he, <hi>must be men of an Ʋpper House, the Peeres of the Church p.</hi> 88. Of his divine Right of Episcopacy; or as he stret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches <hi>Hieromes</hi> expression to justifie the tyranny of some Bishops, <hi>A Bishop must be as a Generall in an Army, who hath power both to Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shall all the Troopes, and to command the Captaines and Colonels, and to execute Marshall-Law upon Officers. p.</hi> 120. Oh you see what the Bishops affect, beware, beware in these bloudy times, lest the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops execute Marshall Law upon you, if you will not list your selfe in some of their Troopes, and fight under their Colours, the <hi>Black-Crosse</hi> displayed in <hi>Aceldama</hi> a field of blood; Sure such conceits as these of executing Marshall-Law, &amp;c. never entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Saint <hi>Hieroms</hi> phantasie, whilest he was awake. What ever this Bishop can take together out of suspected; nay, illegitimate passa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges fathered upon ancient and famous Authors, all that he urges up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us to assent and subscribe unto, in favour of our <hi>Lord-Prelates,</hi> wee must beleeve (when wee are at leasure) that <hi>Ignatius</hi> the Martyr said<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, that a <hi>Bishop beares the resemblance of God the Father, that hee is superiour to all Principality and Power, and therefore we must be subject to the Bishop as unto the Lord, and to the Priests as to the Apostles.</hi> And <hi>what proportion is there</hi> (saith Bishop <hi>Hall) betwixt the respects we owe to God and to man▪ p.</hi> 136. But do you heare <hi>Lord Prelate,</hi> is not this blasphemy? And must a Bishop be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged Superiour to all principality and power (I will give you leave to put in what you have left out) in causes Ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call? Is not this a denyall of the Kings Supremacy in causes Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siasticall? Doe you not maintaine that <hi>Caesar</hi> must obey the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop? <hi>pag.</hi> 142. and is not that your meaning also, <hi>p.</hi> 143. when you say, <hi>Princes must yeeld their necks to the yoke of Christ? &amp;c.</hi> You sshould first have proved that the yoke which the Bishops have of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:111697:4"/> late imposed on Princes, and their people, is the yoke of Christ. Sure I am if Presbyters should use the same speeches to Princes which the Martyred Saints used to their Heathen persecutors, you would have accused them of treason, but it seemes Bishops may use them, and make as bold with Kings, as <hi>Ʋalentinian</hi> and <hi>Traian</hi> did with <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lens;</hi> but Bishops cannot be accused of Treason, because they are in your opinion Superiour to all Principality and Power: or as <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie Taylor</hi> hath it, <hi>The Bishop is in a Peerelesse, an incomparable Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and all the whole Diocesse are his Subjects, in Regimine Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuali:</hi> Episcopacy asserted, <hi>p.</hi> 213. and 214. and the same Master <hi>Taylour</hi> construes that of <hi>Ambrose</hi> to the great advantage of the Bishops, <hi>Pasce oves meas, unde regendae sacerdotibus contraduntur, m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rito Rectoribus suis subdi dicuntur,</hi> and the sheep are delivered <hi>to Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops, as to Rulers, and are made their Subjects, p.</hi> 213. Another man would have said no more, but that the sheepe or people are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their Rectors, for so ordinary Pastours are usually entituled; but these Factors for Prelacy must in stead of feeding the sheepe feed the pride, and excuse the tyranny of the Prelates. I know Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor <hi>Hall,</hi> and <hi>Ieremy Taylour,</hi> pretend to reduce Episcopacy to the Primitive Consistence, but they take some forged testimonies for Primitive testimonies: witnesse those passages of <hi>Ignatius</hi> formerly mentioned, which are foysted in by Interpolation; witnesse those Canons, which they call the Canons of the Apostles; and witnesse those Apostolicall Constitutions, as they terme them, under the name of Saint <hi>Clement,</hi> Nay, Master <hi>Taylour</hi> will adventure as farre as the decretall Epistles, and builds much upon the confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations of Saint <hi>Rembert,</hi> and Saint <hi>Malchus</hi> ratified by miracles, Saint <hi>Clements</hi> Epistle to Saint <hi>Iames,</hi> translated by <hi>Ruffinus;</hi> I need say nothing of <hi>S. Dionysius, Dorotheus</hi> and the rest. Master <hi>Taylors</hi> Booke is exceedingly cryed up, and it is published by his Majesties command, but truly I see nothing new in it, but what stinkes of <hi>Prelaticall Popery;</hi> his argument drawne from Episcopall <hi>confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, consignation, Chrismation,</hi> is new, because newly translated out of Popish Authors, and if the Prelaticall party had not been posting towards <hi>Rome,</hi> he durst not have urged it. The giving of the Holy Ghost by imposition of the Apostles hands, was not, saith Master <hi>Taylor,</hi> for a Miraculous gift, but an ordinary grace, which ordinary grace is to be still conferred upon the Church; but it
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:111697:5"/> cannot be conferred by Presbyters, therefore it is necessary that there should be Bishops, Prelates, in the Church to conferre this grace of Consigning or Confirmation. The Ministery of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit (which hee saith) is the ordinary Office of giving the Holy Ghost by Imposition of hands, is proper and peculiar to Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, read his Episcopacy asserted from <hi>p.</hi> 28. to 35. He would have new baptized people to be brought to the Bishop, that by <hi>Imposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his hands, they may obtaine the Holy Ghost, and so have a supply made of what was wanting after Baptisme, p.</hi> 34.</p>
            <p>And he concludes that it was the <hi>beliefe of Christendome that the Holy Ghost was by no ordinary Ministery given to faithful people after Baptisme,</hi> but onely by Apostolicall or Episcopall Consignation and imposition of hands, in the same 34. page. But it were worth the while, to enquire what this Episcopall Consignation is which the man contends for, it belongs he saith <hi>to the ordinary office of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stleship, an office above Presbyters, but an office to be continued in the Church, and therefore there must be Prelates in the Church,</hi> that this so necessary an office may be performed, pag. 35. But you must turn a great many leaves before hee will acquaint you with the secret, and therefore to save you a labour, I will point you to the places you must observe out of him, that there <hi>is a three-fold Chrismation;</hi> the first is in Baptisme, wherein the Priest doth <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signe the forehead of the child with oyntment in the forme of a Crosse</hi> (for he tells you, that <hi>Consignari</hi> is used in Antiquity for <hi>any sign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the Crosse or annealing,</hi> pa. 206.) and this may, by the leave and favour of the Bishop, be done by a Priest or Presbyter; But this Chrisme or <hi>oyntment must be composed and consecrated by the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop,</hi> and fetcht from the Bishop by the Deacons for the use of all Churches, <hi>Chrisma confectum ab Episcopo,</hi> pag. 207. <hi>Consecratum ab Episcopo,</hi> pag. 208. But you must conceive that this Chrisme in the fore-head is a ceremony of Baptisme, and not of Confirmation, for Confirmation is peculiar to the Prelate, pag. 206. And Unction or Chrismation is especially to be used in Confirmation after Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisme, <hi>Sacramentum Chrismatis</hi> is the usuall word for Confirmation, pag. 205. <hi>Behold a new Sacrament for to make supply of what was wanting in Baptisme, and this supply can be made onely by a Prelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Consignation:</hi> But lest the glosse upon the Canon Law should be lesse popish then Mr. <hi>Taylour,</hi> he remembers that the Presbyters
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:111697:5"/> may confirme their Auditors by Confirmation of Faith, but the Prelates onely by Consignation of Chrisme, pag. 203. <hi>Well, give us the Confirmation of Faith, and let them take the Consignation of Chrisme,</hi> the members of the distinction are surely opposite; it seems then that <hi>the Bishops doe confirme men without Confirmation of their Faith,</hi> they confirm men in Rite and mystery, the presbyters in Faith and Doctrine by their preaching, pag. 203. Bishops in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed have not used to preach of late, but stay, is not this <hi>Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in faith by the Ministery of the Spirit?</hi> and is it not a confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on after Baptisme? why, sure then <hi>we need not to have any Bishops to consigne or anneale the Baptized people,</hi> and then what is become of this goodly argument? Nay farther, Mr. <hi>Taylour</hi> confesses, that there was a long dispute between the Greek and Latine Churches, whether persons confirmed by Presbyters should be reconfirmed, pag. 201. I hasten to the third Chrismation, and that is in plaine English, extreame Vnction, which is the <hi>annealing of a dying body, and a part of Reconciliation</hi> (that's English) which in case of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream necessity is permitted to Presbyters, pag. 206, 207. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve the Church of Christ may enjoy the Ministery of the Spirit by the powerfull preaching, &amp;c. of Presbyters without any one of these three kinds of Chrismation; and therefore the Church may flourish without Prelates.</p>
            <p>Behold Mr. <hi>Taylours</hi> grand Argument lyes speechlesse, but hee hopes to set up the Prelates higher yet, by conferring upon them a <hi>Legislative Power,</hi> that he may the better establish their Authority of <hi>Cognition</hi> of causes, and <hi>Coertion</hi> of persons, whether Lay-men or Clergy-men. The Presbyters, and Clergy, and Laity must obey, (saith Mr. <hi>Taylour</hi>) therefore the Bishop must <hi>govern and give them Lawes,</hi> pag. 220. It is, if you will beleeve him, <hi>a great part of Christianity to honour and obey the Bishops,</hi> pag. 214. <hi>It is a fault to remaine in Virginity without the Bishops leave,</hi> pag. 216. it seemes Virginity is of <hi>Prelaticall Cognizance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Presbyters are hardly used, but the Lay-men are much more abused. The Presbyters (hee saith) at the most can but rule in conjunction and assistance, but ever in subordination to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop, the Laity must obey <hi>de Integro;</hi> (be wholly subject to the Bishop) For that is to keep them in that state, in which God hath placed them, pag. 219. Mr. <hi>Taylour</hi> cannot deny but that the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:111697:6"/> Presbyters were termed συνέδρευται και σύμβουλοι τ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ν Επισκόπων, Counsellours and Assessours with the Bishop in <hi>Igna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ius</hi> his time and yet he would faine reserve the Superio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ity of Iurisdiction to the Bishop, and that <hi>Absolutely and Independently of conjunction with the Presbytery,</hi> pag. 225. It seemes the Bishops affect an <hi>inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendencie,</hi> and therefore are so angry with those Ministers who are termed <hi>Independents.</hi> He talkes much of <hi>Cyprian,</hi> but it is clear and evident that <hi>Cyprian</hi> did not affect that Absolute Independency which Mr. <hi>Taylour</hi> contends for; it is true that <hi>Cyprian</hi> being chosen <hi>Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>positus</hi> or President of the Presbytery, he took it to heart that they contemned and reviled him whom they had chosen to be their <hi>Praepositus,</hi> Provo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> or President, and that the Presbyters did challenge the whole Authority and reserve it to themselves; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as they were not a Presbytery without their President; <hi>Quod nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam omnino sub Antecessoribus factum est, ut cum contumelia &amp; contemptu Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>posititotum sibi vendicent Presbyteri:</hi> These are <hi>Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> words, and what is there here to prove that a Bishop, Provost, President is Independent upon a Presbytery? Mr. <hi>Taylour</hi> urges a great many passages out of the Acts of severall Councels; but who over denyed that Bishops did magnifie their owne Authority? or who that is wise would make them Iudges in their owne cause? Truly it is ridiculous to endeavour to prove what was the <hi>constant practise of Primitive Christendome</hi> out of the Canons of Councels; and to say that provinciall Councels are made Catholike by adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and inserting them into the <hi>Code of the Catholike Church</hi> is to out-speake the Iesuites themselves, and yet these are Mr. <hi>Taylours</hi> expressions, pag. 234. And I wonder much that Mr. <hi>Taylour</hi> hath so little forehead to affirme that he can finde no presbyters joyning either in Commission or Fact, in power or exercise with Bishops, but that Censures are appropriated to Bishops. Hee speakes more to the purpose when he saith that the Canons of Councels were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by secular Authority, as appeares in the Imperiall Consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions, pag. 235. and then from all his allegations he may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed inferre this conclusion, that prelates were established between three and foure hundred yeares after Christ by secular Authority; but what is this to the point in hand, namely, to shew the <hi>constant practise of Primitive Christendome?</hi> or to shew that Prelacie is <hi>Iure Divino?</hi> But because Mr. <hi>Taylour</hi> hath laid so much weight
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:111697:6"/> upon the ancient Canons (as he calls them) let us, if you will, see what is that Canonicall power conferred upon Bishops. The an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Canons (saith he) asserting the Bishops power <hi>in cognitione causarum</hi> speake in most large and comprehensive tearmes, και οἴ τ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> θέλωσιν ἐξουσίαν ἔκουσι, <hi>They have power to doe what they list, their Power is as large as their Will,</hi> pag. 235. Behold an Arbitrary Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, Bishops may doe what they list in the determining of all controversies which concern Church affaires, and judging of all causes that are of Ecclesiasticall cognizance; Now <hi>those things which christianity</hi> (as it prescinds from the interest of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth) <hi>hath introduced, all them and all the causes emergent from them, the Bishop is Judge of, such as are causes of Faith, Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration of Sacraments and Sacramentalls, Subordination of inferiour Clergy to their superiour, censures, Irregularities, Orders Hierarchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, Rites and ceremonies, Liturgies and publike formes of Prayer, Dispensation of Church-vessels, Ornaments and goods, receiving and disposing of the Patrimony of the Church,</hi> and whatsoever is of the same consideration, p. 237. Here's ample power indeed, the Bishop may doe what he pleases in all these and the like matters, for he is in the language of the Iesuites <hi>our Superiour,</hi> and therefore Mr. <hi>Tay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour</hi> talkes of the <hi>Subordination of the Inferiour Clergy to their Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour,</hi> the Bishop must be acknowledged, as <hi>Leontius</hi> was called, ὁ κανὼν τῆς Εκκλησίας, the Canon or rule of the Church; what need we then to have Canonicall Scripture for our rule? I cannot stand to reckon up all the swelling Titles of the Prelates. All pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er (saith Mr. <hi>Taylour</hi>) is derived from Christ, now Kings are Christs Vicars in his Regall power, but Bishops are Christs Vicars in his Sacerdotall and propheticall power, pag. 245. Sure I am he hath not set the Kings Throne very fast on this foundation, for Christ saith, his Kingdome was not of this World, must the King conclude from hence, that he must have no Kingdome in this world? And it is not very sure that Prelates are Christs Vicars in his priest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Office, unlesse they will say that they are priests after the Order of <hi>Melchisedech,</hi> or that Christ had a changeable and no eternall priesthood, or finally are willing that Prelates should be crucified as Christ was. But though Lord-prelates have such preheminence, yet Mr. <hi>Taylour</hi> tells us that the Presbyter challenges an higher power, because the Booke of Order of Excommunication in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:111697:7"/> assures him, that the Presbytery doth censure men for Murther, Treason, Witch-craft, &amp;c. Nay, they think <hi>every action of any man to have in it the malignity of a damnable sinne, pag</hi> 250. Nay, they nullifie all Courts and Iudicatories besides their own, <hi>Ib.</hi> sure he transcribed these two last accusations out of some Iesuite; doth Mr <hi>Taylour</hi> think any action performed by us in the state of imperfection to be perfectly pure as it comes from us? is there no culpable defect adherent to our best actions? and yet we doe not excommunicate any man for such defects. It may be Mr <hi>Taylour</hi> hath a farther reach, and thinks some sinnes are not <hi>mortall,</hi> but in their own nature <hi>veniall.</hi> I will not expatiate any farther lest I follow him in his digressions, but because he scoffes so much at Presbyterie wee will examine whether there may not be more said for Presbyteriall Government, then he or any other can say against it.</p>
            <p>In that Apostolicall List of Church Officers, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. and <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip.</hi> 1. either Prelates are left out, or preaching Presbyters: but it is cleare and evident that the Apostle doth every where allow of preaching Presbyters, therefore the Prelates are left out. I hope we may urge <hi>Philip.</hi> 1.1. though I know it was urged by <hi>Aerius,</hi> the place is cleare to prove that the Church did then consist of <hi>Saints, Deacons,</hi> and <hi>Presbyters,</hi> and it is so cleare that <hi>Epiphanius</hi> who condemned <hi>Aerius,</hi> was forced to acknowledge that there was no Bishop at the first placed in that and other Churches; St <hi>Hierome</hi> saith the same, and <hi>Saravia</hi> confesses that <hi>Epiphanius</hi> is mistaken more then once in those positions which he layes down instead of answers to the arguments of <hi>Aerius, vide Saraviam de divers grad. cap.</hi> 22. If a Bishop hath so great a power, as the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laticall men say he hath, then we need only prove that in the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of the Apostle a Presbyter and a Bishop are both one, and therefore they are of equall Authority. But this you will say, is the heresie of <hi>Aerius.</hi> I answer first, that reverend <hi>Beza</hi> doth defend <hi>Aerius</hi> against <hi>Epiphanius</hi> in this point: Secondly, learned <hi>Iewel,</hi> though a Bishop, defends <hi>Aerius</hi> against <hi>Harding:</hi> What saith Bishop <hi>Jewel,</hi> is it so horrible an heresie to say, that by the Scriptures of God, a Bishop and a Priest (or Presbyter) are all one? Thirdly, Bishop <hi>Jewel</hi> cites <hi>Chrysostome, Hierome, Augustine, Ambrose,</hi> and saith, these, and many more holy Fathers together with
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:111697:7"/> St. <hi>Paul</hi> the Apostle for thus saying, must by Master <hi>Harding's</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, be condemned for Heretiks. <hi>Iewels Def. Apolog. part.</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 202. <hi>Medina</hi> addes <hi>Primasius, Oecumenius, Sedulius, Theodoret,</hi> and <hi>Theophylact. Medin l.</hi> 1. <hi>de sacrorum hominum origine &amp; continentia, cap.</hi> 5. <hi>Chysostome,</hi> considering that place, <hi>Philip.</hi> 1.1. saith there were not many Bishops in one City, ἀλλὰ τοὺς πρεσβυτέρους, he called the Presbyters, Bishops: Some cite that of St <hi>Hierome,</hi> to put a difference between Bishops and Presbyters, <hi>Quid enim facit exceptâ ordinatione Episcopus quod Presbyter non faciat?</hi> But these men must not stand to this rule, unlesse they will lose their Jurisdiction, whilest they contend for Ordination. Besides, this Reservation was a meer Usurpation, for the Presbyters did ordain by Imposition of hands in the time of the Apostle, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14. <hi>By the hands of the Presbytery; Beza</hi> observes that some would faine turne πρεσβυτ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ριον into <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>πιοκοπεῖον, nay the hands of the Presbytery into the hands of the Prelate, for the Prelate challenges sole Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi> stands much upon <hi>Cyprians</hi> authority in this point; Now what <hi>Cyprian</hi> meant by Presbytery is so cleare in his third Book, <hi>Epist.</hi> 11. that <hi>Saravia</hi> confesses <hi>Cyprian</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood πρεβυτ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ριον to be an Assembly of Presbyters; <hi>Fateor Cypria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num Presbyterii voce significass<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> Confessum Presbyterorum, <hi>vide Sarav. de grad. Ministr. cap.</hi> 22. <hi>pag.</hi> 213. <hi>Aerius</hi> then was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justly condemned for saying that Presbyters might ordaine; this place of <hi>Timothy</hi> in the judgement of <hi>Cyprian</hi> and many Ancients more, proves that Presbyters may ordaine: Besides, we have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother instance for it in the Church of <hi>Antioch,</hi> there were certain Prophets and Teachers, who laid their hands upon <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Barna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas,</hi> and separated them to the work of the Ministery whereunto God called them, &amp; they did ordain <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> by the command of the Holy Ghost, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.1.2.3. who dares deny that this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation was complete? and yet there was no Apostle nor Prelate pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent at this Ordination: And what are the Ministers in the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches (where there are no Prelates) no Ministers, because they are ordained without a Prelate? The Canon Law which our Prelates would faine have established, doth permit an Abbat to Ordaine if he be a Presbyter, that's all the Law requires, <hi>dist.</hi> 69. <hi>c. Quoniam,</hi> (let them leave citing the Decretall Epistles, if they will not admit of that Canon Law) <hi>Abbati manuum impositio con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceditur
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:111697:8"/> dum constet illum esse Presbyterum:</hi> But enough of that, I passe to Iurisdicton, and here wee shall have our Prelaticall men citing the Decretall Epistles thick and threefold, but <hi>Duarenus de Benef. Eccles. in Prooemio</hi> observes that most of the Decretall Epistles which concerne Iurisdiction were written to English Prelates, and therefore they are but so many Catholike complements, not Dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall Resolutions, as Mr <hi>Taylor</hi> would have them: But you'l say they cite many Fathers in this argument; First, we know that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Fathers have erred in matters of faith, and it is more likely they should erre in matters of Fact, because we doe rely upon humane testimony (which is very deceitfull) for matter of Fact. If any one that is reverenced for Antiquity and Piety hath been too credulous, and hath taken up some relations upon trust without due examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that one man may deceive an hundred, and then if we will reckon right, the hundred testimonies of succeeding Writers is virtually and in a rationall account, but the Testimony of that one man, upon whose credit all their Relations doe depend. Secondly, it is well known that when the Fathers ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in their Rhetoricall veine, they use many <hi>Hyperbole's</hi> which will not hold weight with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a graine or two of favourable allowance. I remember <hi>Hieromes</hi> excuse, <hi>Rhetoricati sumus, &amp; in modum declamatorium paululum lusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, Hieronym. adv. Helvidium</hi>—ludicious <hi>Rivet</hi> in his tract <hi>de Patrum Authoritate pag.</hi> 67. passes this grave censure, <hi>Rhetorican<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur interdum Patres vehementius vel in exhortationibus, vel in Favorem aliorum;</hi> if they are apt to over-lash in favour of others, certainly they are most apt to exceed in favour of themselves, or at least them of their own ranke and order. Thirdly, the Fathers seldome entred into a controversie, but they ranne too farre from their Adversary, and left the truth in the middle between them and their Adversary. Now the Fathers who lived in the time of <hi>Aerius</hi> and since, have in opposition to <hi>Aerius</hi> extolled Bishops more highly then they ought. Fourthly, that of learned <hi>Casaubon</hi> is very considerable, the Fathers handle some things διδακτικῶς, and some ὀικονο<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap>ως, <hi>dum proposito suo serviunt vide Casaub. Annot. ad Epist. G. Nyss. ad Amb &amp; Bas. pag.</hi> 88. <hi>&amp;</hi> 89. Now that some of the Fathers did <hi>proposito suo inservire,</hi> in handling the cause of Bishops, is out of doubt, and others might be easily drawn into the same dissimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as good <hi>Barnabas</hi> once was, <hi>Galat.</hi> 2.13. And yet I reverence
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:111697:8"/> Antiquity as highly as the most reverend Fathers desire mee to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence it; Concerning the Catologue of Bishops, see <hi>Augustines</hi> Epistle, 15<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>ad Generosum;</hi> Give me leave to begin with Scripture, and I will sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w enough out of Antiquity in the close. The Prelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call men talke much of the Angels in the Revelation, much might be said, but I think this sufficient, the Angell of <hi>Ephesus</hi> was no Prelate, for all the Presbyters of <hi>Ephesus</hi> are stiled Bishops, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is the word, and had power of Government given them by the Holy Ghost, if <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> import Government, as the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laticall men say it doth, read <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28. St <hi>Hierom</hi> proves from this place and three more, that a Bishop and a Presbyter are the same in name and power. When St <hi>Peter</hi> speaks of that ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary power in which the Ministers of the Gospel succeed the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles, he calls himselfe a Presbyter, and exhorts the Presbyters in high language, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.1.2. and he would not have them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, v. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. they might have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, had there been any Prelates over them in those dayes, Alas, alas, the Prelates are more likely to Lord it over us and the people, give this counsell to the Prelates, they stand in more need of it.</p>
            <p>I wonder that men that have been bred in an University should explode and scoffe at a Collegiate Government by a Colledge of Pastours and a President. Againe, I admire that men should fancie that to erect a Presbytery, is to set up a Government which is more Prelaticall then the Prelacy it selfe; for in a Presbytery there is a Priority of Order in the President to avoid confusion, but no Prelaticall Authority to avoid Tyranny, <hi>there is no chaire for Diotrephes there.</hi> Finally, wee utterly disavow the maintaining of the <hi>Independency of a Presbyteriall Church,</hi> because we main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the use of Synods to be lawfull and necessary, nor doe wee maintain an <hi>Independancy of Synods, for the word is their Rule.</hi> It is clear and evident by the light of nature, <hi>that the part must be in sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to those who command the whole,</hi> all the Members of this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation must be subject to the Guides, Governours, &amp; Overseers of this Congregation, &amp; all the Members of this &amp; the Sister-Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations are subject to the Presbytery, many Presbyteries subject to a Provinciall Assembly, &amp; all the Provinces of the Nation subject to a Nationall Synod, and the Synod subject to the holy Ghost speaking in the word; is not here order, equity, decency? Why do men then
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:111697:9"/> talk of Anarchy, or dream of a popular Government by the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny-headed multitude, as if all should runne into confusion, and there should be an absolute Parity, and no Order, or decency at all if Prelacy be extirpated? Away with such vaine conceits, it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent by what hath been said, <hi>that distances will be observed, secundum sub &amp; supra, still;</hi> But the great objection is that Prelacy was at first instituted to suppresse Schismes, and therefore if once Prelacy be extirpated, all manner of Sects and Schismes will arise in the Church: I answer, wee know by sad experience, that the Prelates have been the <hi>Ring-leaders of an Antichristian Schisme:</hi> and we know by good experience, that the Church and Kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> is more firmly united under the Presbyteriall Government, then <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> hath been under the Prelaticall; no sooner doth a Sect or a Schismatique peep out in <hi>Scotland,</hi> but presently they are nipt by the Presbytery: And if Prelacy was first invented and Bishops prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to hinder Schisme, surely since Prelates are become the greatest Schismatiques, Incendiaries, Prelacy may be abolished (since nothing else will serve the turn) that the Schism which the Prelates themselves have made &amp; strengthned, may be timely quelled. The power of the Keyes in the hand of a Presbytery or Synod is sufficient to quell both Hereticks and Schismatiques: if a Schisme hath rent a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince or a Nation to pieces, that Province and Nation is bound by the Word of God, the Dictates of sound reason and Christian pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to stand to the Decrees of a Provintiall or Nationall Synod, so farre forth as these Decrees are agreeable to the Word of God, for so farre and no farther doe they bind. Let Mr <hi>Taylor</hi> consider that of St <hi>Cyprian</hi> in his third Book and 19<seg rend="sup">th</seg> Epistle, and then hee will confesse with <hi>Cyprian,</hi> that one Prelate is not sufficient to cure a Provinciall Schisme: <hi>Quae res cùm omnium nostrum consilium &amp; sententiam spectet,</hi> praejudicare ego, &amp; solùm mihi rem com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munem vendicate non audeo. And let him construe that of <hi>Augustine, Peregrinus</hi> Presbyter &amp; Seniores <hi>Ecclesiae Musticanae regionis, &amp;c. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>contra Cresconium, cap.</hi> 56. Or that of <hi>Tertulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, Cum Presbyterii ordine praesident probati qui{que} Seniores honorem istum non pretio sed testimonio adepti. Apolog cap.</hi> 39. There is a two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold θεραπεία, or Ministry, saith <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus,</hi> βελτιωτικὴ and ύπηρετικὴ: the first he saith belongs to Presbyters, the second to Deacons; now βελτιωτικὴ, being opposed to ύπηρετικὴ, must necessari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:111697:9"/> imply an Authoritative jurisdiction: he saith nothing of a third kind of Ministery; this θεραπεία βελτιωτικὴ was to <hi>better the people, not onely by perswasion, but by jurisdiction,</hi> for he saith the Deacons were to attend upon the Presbyters, as children upon their Parents, as ordinary men upon Governours. <hi>Vide Clem Alexand. Stromat. l.</hi> 7. <hi>non procul ab initio p</hi> 700. Bishop <hi>Hall</hi> acknowledges that it doth appeare by the observations of <hi>Iustellus,</hi> and the two learned <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saubons,</hi> that there were <hi>Seniores Ecclesiastici</hi> in the Church of old, and he is forced to confesse that they were not onely <hi>Seniores Popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li,</hi> as Magistrates or Aldermen of Incorporate Townes and Cities, but <hi>Seniores Ecclesiae,</hi> or <hi>Ecclesiastici;</hi> and his conceit is ridiculous to dream that such men so renowned were but Church-wardens, he is glad to adde, or Vestry-men at the highest, &amp; so doth in effect grant the whole question concerning Vestry-Elders, read his Reply to <hi>Smectymnuus, pag.</hi> 146. What will they say to <hi>Cyprians</hi> distinction betweene Presbyters and Seniors, when he complaines that the Presbyters were too supercilious, taking upon them to doe so much <hi>absque consensu Seniorum?</hi> I beleeve it will trouble them to answer that question: but they will be more troubled to answer all those Ancient Records which are pressed home by that learned Antiqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Salmasius.</hi> I will not enter into that dispute, whether there be a twofold power of the Keyes, <hi>potestas concionalis,</hi> and <hi>potestas Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plinaria?</hi> or whether it be a Pastorall Act to define or determine any thing in Synods and Councels? or whether there be not a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betweene Pastorall teaching, and Synodicall teaching? whether a Lay-man being Elected a Commissioner to propound, Reason, and Vote in a Synod, in the behalfe of some Congregation, be not a kind of Ecclesiasticall person, in regard of that Office whereunto he is elected and deputed? and finally, whether if a wholesome constitution should be carryed and decreed by the Vote of such a person, helping to make the major part in a Synod, that wholesome Decree doth not bind the people Ecclesiastically in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the Authority of them who composed it, as well as Mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rially, or rather Morally, because the matter of the Decree is agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Word of God? I must wave these questions and divers others, &amp; passe to the next Prelaticall errour, Their Canonizing or Idolizing of that Service-booke, which the most judicious Divines of the Reformed Churches have ever looked upon as a Pageant
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:111697:10"/> tricked up with tolerable, or (as others) <hi>intolerable fooleries, a Masse of Superstition, a Magazine of Ceremonies, the lazy Church-mans Pillow, the blind-Church-maens Spectacles, the lame Church-mans Crutches, and the Common peoples Idol.</hi> Nay, some Masse mongers amongst us to testifie their compliance with <hi>Rome,</hi> have not been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid to speake out in the reigne of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and call it <hi>Masse in English,</hi> witnesse <hi>Cozens, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ecklington, Mountague▪</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd others. I need say nothing of the letter o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Pope <hi>Pius</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e 4. for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onfirmation of the Service booke, you may see enough in <hi>Br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>stowes</hi> Motives or <hi>Carriers</hi> Considerations; Nor need I take notice of the Letter of King <hi>Edward</hi> the 6. to the Papists of <hi>Cornwall</hi> and <hi>Devonshire,</hi> written by the advice of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ouncell; these things have beene largely insisted on by others. But I would fain have any man prove that when men began to call upon the Name of the Lord at the first in the dayes of <hi>Enos, Gen.</hi> 4.26. that then they had a Set-forme im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed upon them; Now certainly the Spirit of Supplication since the Ascension of the Lord Iesus is more plentifully powred forth upon the Church, &amp; therfore if men be forced <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o read a Dead-form, and pray by Booke in these dayes of light and glory, there will sad effects and consequences follow upon such a rigorous Imposition &amp; constraint. It is evident by lamentable experience that divers Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters of happy parts and excellent gifts by the use of this Dead-forme in the Service-Booke, have beene utterly disabled to pray af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a Spirituall manner upon solemne, but unexpected occasions; their parts have beene dryed up, and withered, their gifts blasted, their spirit straitned in such a fearefull manner, as may well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter any man from tying himselfe to a Service-Booke, and neglecting those parts and gifts which God hath out of his free bounty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowed upon him, lest God punish his neglect and unthankfulnesse, after such a remarkeable manner as may make him an example to all posterity. I presume no man will defend that order in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer Booke, for the reading of <hi>Apocrypha,</hi> and omitting di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers parts of Canonicall Scripture; it is a sinne that cryes to Heaven for vengeance upon this Nation, that wee have by such a solemn Order preferred the <hi>Apocrypha</hi> before the Word of God, as if the inventions and (to say truth) the fooleries of men did tend <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e to edification then the Scriptures, which were written by the Divin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> inspiration of the Holy Ghost. Nor is it possible to excuse
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:111697:10"/> many ridiculous passages in that Translation of Scripture which is retained in the Common-Prayer. Book; witnesse that Passage, <hi>And Easter a Feast of the Iewes was nigh;</hi> and that of <hi>Galat.</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.20. where <hi>they make zeale a fruit of the flesh,</hi> which perchance is the reason, why the Prelaticall men have been so constantly obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the common people when they have inveighed against zeale; sure the common people have taken this Translation for the Word of God, and looked upon zeale as a fruit of the flesh which would pollute and defile them, and therefore there is so little zeale in those Countreys where they have had no other service, then what is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in this Service Book. Moreover, they have in the Epistle for the Sunday after Christmasse-day falsly, if not blasphemously and Heretically translated <hi>Galath.</hi> 4.5. <hi>That we through Election</hi> might <hi>receive the Adoption that belongs to naturall Sonnes,</hi> an arrant con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, and as we use to call it, a <hi>Bull,</hi> for no naturall Sonne can be said to be adopted, nor is any adopted sonne a naturall sonne; Nothing but Generation can make a man a naturall son. Now none but the Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>esus is the naturall Sonne of God. The true Translation is, <hi>That we might receive the Adoption of Sonnes.</hi> Now the adopted Sonnes of God are in that very verse opposed to his naturall Sonne spoken of in the former verse, God hath sent forth his own Sonne, vers. 4. that is, his naturall Sonne; but enough of that; And they might have followed a better Translation of <hi>Galat.</hi> 5.19.20. which runnes thus, The works of the flesh are manifest, &amp;c.—hatred, variance, <hi>emulations,</hi> wrath, strife, seditions, <hi>heresies;</hi> and not as they read in their Epistle for the 14<seg rend="sup">th</seg> Sunday after Trinity▪ The deeds of the flesh are manifest, &amp;c. <hi>Hatred, va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riance, zeale,</hi> wrath, strife, seditions, <hi>Sects, in stead of Heresies;</hi> our <hi>Arminians</hi> tell us, that Hereticks are pious and innocent men, and therefore not punishable. They follow the Masse book in Transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Luke</hi> 1.28. Haile thou that art <hi>full of grace,</hi> in stead of Haile thou that art <hi>highly favoured:</hi> and so <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.48. Hee hath regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>the lowlinesse,</hi> in stead of the <hi>low estate;</hi> as if the blessed Virgin had merited to be the Mother of God by her humility and lowli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of minde; the Word in the Originall is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. I cannot omit their Translation of <hi>Psalm.</hi> 105.28. <hi>They were not obedient to his word,</hi> but the Holy Ghost declares the contrary, and saith, <hi>they rebelled not against his word.</hi> In the Gospel
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:111697:11"/> for St <hi>Luke</hi>'s day, they Translate <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.1. The Lord <hi>appointed other seventy and two,</hi> whereas the holy Ghost saith the Lord <hi>appointed other seventy,</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y take the boldnesse to adde two more then the holy Ghost sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ks of. Now this fault is the more inexcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sable because there is a purer Translation of the Scriptures, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished by Authority, and yet the Prelates have still retained these grosse corruptions.</p>
            <p>I wonder that they should all this while connive at such an intolerable disagreement between the Translations, I will give but one instance more, in the Psalmes in the Common-Prayer-Book, <hi>Psal.</hi> 58.8. we read, <hi>so let indignation vex him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ven as a thing that is raw,</hi> in stead of these words, <hi>He shall take them away as with a whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lwind both living and in his wrath,</hi> as you may see by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring it with our new Translation; but observe that it is the ninth verse in the New-Translation. Besides, there is no sense in that Liturgicall Translation, <hi>Or ever your pots be made hot with thorns, so let indignation vex him even as a thing that is raw.</hi> The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people (hearing that there is only a directory for Worship in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, as appears by the late Covenant) conceive that they shall be deprived of whatsoever is in the Common-Prayer-Book; but they should consider that the Common-Prayer-Book containes things of very different natures, Creeds, Commandments, Psalms, Prayers, &amp;c. Now the Parliament never intends to take away the Psalmes, Commandments, or those parts of Scripture which are called Epistles and Gospels, but the people shall enjoy these in a more faithfull Translation in their Bibles, and have them familiarly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded and powerfully applyed to their consciences by able and conscionable Ministers; for the Parliament daily seeks for such to instruct the people, but the Prelates would never allow of any such Translation in the <hi>Service-Book,</hi> or such an exercise as the expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Commandments, &amp;c. <hi>They counted that as bad as Preaching.</hi> Nay, the Parliament intends not to take away the Creeds, for though they be not parts of Scripture, yet because the sum and substance of them was collected out of Scripture, the Creeds shall be retained, and those obscure phrases which might occasion a mistake, namely, the Descent into Hell, &amp;c. shall be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained agreeable to the Word of God, and the Analogy of faith. Moreover, we must put a great deale of difference between the Lords
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:111697:11"/> Prayer, and Prayers composed by man; <hi>The Parliament will not take away the Lords prayer, nor forbid the use of it;</hi> and if some prayers (composed by men subject to mistakes) which are many of them rather <hi>good wishes then Prayers,</hi> be omitted, there will be no great want of them, considering first, that though there are many <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian prayers,</hi> in regard of the expressions, yet the whole body of them hath ever by the Prelaticall party been designed <hi>to an Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christian use,</hi> namely to nourish an ignorant lazy and ambitious Clergy, for the Non-Residents by this meanes doe only pay for a Reading Curate, and are allowed to bee Non-Residents: Secondly, that they were composed in times of ignorance, for the help of Ministers almost as ignorant as the common people: Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that God hath now furnished his Church with men of excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent parts and gifts, <hi>Who are able to pray as well as preach upon all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions,</hi> and it were as great pity to hinder the exercise of these mens gifts by making a <hi>Prayer for them, as by making a Sermon for them;</hi> the one is as great a shame to them and damp to their Spirits as the other: and the State may as well forbid them to preach a Sermon of their own studying, and tye them to read Homilies, as to forbid them to use a prayer of their own composing, and command them who are truly <hi>Iudicious, Practically holy</hi> and <hi>Experimentally Devout,</hi> to read a prayer out of a book, more like a Schoole-Boy then Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Pastours of the Church of Christ. Nay, if an ingenious School-boy would bee ashamed to read a Declamation composed by another, when he is called to perform that exercise, sure a Minister of Christ will bee more ashamed to have a prayer made for him by Bishops or Arch-Bishops, when the Arch-Shepheard &amp; Bishop of his Soul hath left him, <hi>A pattern of prayer, a rule of prayer, and a Spirit of prayer to help his infirmities, and blesse him with abilities for this great duty of prayer.</hi> It concernes Ministers in this point to imitate the Apostles, <hi>Act.</hi> 6.4. to give <hi>themselves continually to prayer,</hi> as well as to the Ministry of the Word; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is the full expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of the holy Ghost in that place. Can the Prelates teach us to pray better then the holy Ghost? Now the holy Ghost teacheth us <hi>both what and how to pray;</hi> We know not <hi>what to pray</hi> for, <hi>as wee ought,</hi> we are ignorant of <hi>matter and manner;</hi> the holy Ghost helps our infirmities in both, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26. And if the holy Ghost doth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford such assistance to ordinary Christians, sure much more to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:111697:12"/> Pastours whom he hath commanded to give themselves to prayer, and to whom he hath given variety of Pastorall gifts that they may discharge all Pastorall duties. Christ hath sent some <hi>Pastours, some</hi> Teachers <hi>for the perfecting of the Saints,</hi> for the <hi>work of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry,</hi> that the Saints <hi>may be no more Children, Ephes.</hi> 4.11.12.14. Now doth God send Pastours, send them for the work of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistry? and doth hee not inable them for the work of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistry? or is not prayer a work of the Ministry? Is the Pastour sent by God to perfect the Saints, and will not God perfect the Pastour for the performance of pastorall duties, that the Saints may be perfected? Hath God sent Pastours to instruct the Saints that the <hi>Saints may no longer be children,</hi> and must the Pastours still <hi>remaine children, and bee set to read prayers out of book, like very children?</hi> Away with such ridiculous and vaine conceites. But if the common people who have been nursed up in ignorance and superstition, will not part with their old customes, and are resolved to keep this Service-Book, let it bee then considered whether the <hi>Queen and the Prelates and the Romane Catholique-subjects,</hi> (I must not say <hi>Rebels, English and Irish, now after the Irish Pacification,</hi> whom the Queen and the Bishops have stirred up) are likely to pleasure the people in this particular? It is well known that the <hi>great Prelates doe not like this Common-Prayer-Book,</hi> they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed one a great deale worse, and sent it into <hi>Scotland;</hi> I am perswaded the most ignorant people would <hi>lose their dearest bloud rather then receive that Common-Prayer-Book which was sent into Scotland,</hi> and they must expect that or a worse, if the <hi>Bishops may have their will.</hi> And sure if the Queen may prevaile with the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops, or the <hi>Jesuits with the Queen,</hi> the common people shall not have, no not that Common-Prayer-Book (which was sent into <hi>Scotland</hi>) in <hi>English;</hi> they must have it, or the very <hi>Masse,</hi> in Latine, <hi>that's plaine English;</hi> nay, believe it good people, the Queen and her party are likely to take <hi>away not only this Common-Prayer-Book, but even the Bible also, and not leave you so much as the Word of God in English.</hi> Oh, but if the Common-Prayer-Booke bee taken away, what Religion shall wee have? Why sure, that Religion, which Christ and his Apostles had before there was any Common-Prayer-Book, for they left us none, and Christians had none for the first 300 yeeres; Your Religion is many hundred
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:111697:12"/> yeeres more ancient then this Common-Prayer-Book, the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Religion is the old Religion. Bee content then with a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectory, and if any man pray non-sense, blasphemy, &amp;c. hee shall bee punished for not observing the pious and prudent directions given.</p>
            <p>But though <hi>this Forme</hi> prescribed in the Service-Book be a <hi>Dead Form,</hi> yet for their sakes who composed it, <hi>let it be honourably buried.</hi> I need say no more of the Prelaticall errours; all that they have to plead now, is the Law of the Land, and that is much insisted on by some. First, I wonder they should now come to plead <hi>Ius humanum,</hi> who have bragged so much that they were <hi>Iure Divino,</hi> and given out that they would not hold their Bishopricks an houre, if they could not prove that they held them by <hi>Divine Right.</hi> Secondly, This case being propounded to a great Lawyer and Antiquary in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Kingdome, it was resolved by him, <hi>That the Hierarchy ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iured in this Covenant, was never established by Law in England.</hi> Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, though there w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s a Prelacy forged by the Canon-Law, and that Law too much received in time of Popery, yet by the submission of the Clergy in the 25<seg rend="sup">th</seg> of <hi>Henry</hi> the 8<seg rend="sup">th</seg>, that Law was clearely abolished, and consequently all Arch-Bishops, Bishops, Arch-Deacons, &amp;c. depending upon the Authority, and drawn from the grounds and rules of the Canon-Law, are abolished. Fourthly, the Bishops have had power to exercise Iurisdiction in <hi>England</hi> by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the High-Commission, but the Act passed against the exercise of that power in the High-Commission, hath made their Commissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on void, and their Authority of none effect. Fiftly, that Statute of proviso's which they brag of, wil not advantage them, for by that it appeares that they were set up <hi>to informe the people of the Law of God▪ and to make Hospitalities, and Almes, and other works of Charity,</hi> and this they may do still according to their ability. This case be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing propounded to a great Statesman, whether the Prelates, who have engaged themselves in this Antichristian warre, should not have a legall tryall? His answer was, <hi>We give Law to an Hare, but we give a polt to a polt-cat.</hi> Dr <hi>Hall</hi> (as hath been shewn) saith the Bishops <hi>might give Marshall law:</hi> and now it seemes they must <hi>suffer Marshall law.</hi> Sure a Prelate in Armes, and a Prelate Confederate with the <hi>Irish Rebels of the Spanish faction,</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:111697:13"/> may thank himselfe if he get a polt, and will deserve but part of Cardinall <hi>Richelieu</hi> his Epitaph, if he get a victory.</p>
            <q xml:lang="lat">
               <l>Hic jacet</l>
               <l>Sacerdos in Castris;</l>
               <l>Theologus in Aulâ;</l>
               <l>Episcopus sine grege;</l>
               <l>Cardinalis sine galero;</l>
               <l>Rex sine nomine;</l>
               <l>Qui spirare desiit, &amp; Timeri,</l>
               <l>Quo migravit Sacramentum est.</l>
            </q>
            <p>So much for Prelates; <hi>Even so let all thine enemies perish O Lord, but let them that love thee, bee as the Sunne when he goeth forth in his might, that England and Ireland, and all the Reformed Churches may have rest,</hi> Amen, Amen. <hi>Judg.</hi> 5.31.</p>
            <p>But a word or two at this time to the <hi>Antinomians;</hi> for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly they have very little reason to cry out against this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, unlesse they are offended with the Gospel, as well as with the Law; for the sinnes specified in this Covenant are sinnes directly against the Gospel, and will they deny that we are too humbled for sinnes against the Gospel also? who is there who hath not good cause to cry guilty, and acknowledge that he hath not as he ought, <hi>valued the inestimable benefit of the Gospel?</hi> Oh! the under-valuing of the Gospel of the Lord Iesus is a crying sinne, our <hi>sinne will cry, if we doe not.</hi> O let us loath our selves because wee have not laboured <hi>for the purity and power of the Gospel,</hi> that wee have not endeavoured to <hi>receive Christ</hi> in our hearts, nor to <hi>walk worthy</hi> of him in our lives: These, these, are <hi>sinning sinnes,</hi> the causes of other sinnes and transgressions so much abounding amongst us. Doe we not in the close of the Covenant beseech the Lord to strengthen us by his holy Spirit, that we may be enabled to keep this Covenant? <hi>as that a Legall prayer?</hi> O but we swear to preserve the Discipline and Government in the Church of <hi>Scotland;</hi> True, but we sweare <hi>only to preserve it against our common enemies.</hi> and sure the <hi>Antinomians</hi> will grant that the Discipline of the Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> is farre bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then <hi>English Prelacy,</hi> or down right Popery. But are there no defects in that Discipline? admit there be, yet neverthelesse <hi>so farre
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:111697:13"/> forth as they have attained, let it bee preserved:</hi> If the Moone have spots, must it bee plucked from the Firmament? and if a Church have defects, must wee suffer it to be ruined by an Antichristian faction, which seeks the ruine of all Churches which desire a thorow-Reformation. Finally, the Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> is willing to see her defects, if you can shew them, they will give you thanks, and reforme ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Covenant; they desire that all three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes may bee brought to the neerest conjunction and uniformity in Religion and Forme of Church Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment according to the Word of God. It is confessed on all sides, that as the Essentials of Government are prescri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, Instituted, and Constituted in the Word: so there are divers circumstances which are to bee ordered by the generall Rules in the Word, the <hi>particular Cases must be Referred to Christian prudence.</hi> Wee have in this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant many motives set before our eyes; <hi>The glory of God, the advancement of Christs Kingdome, the honour and happinesse of the Kings Majesty and his Posterity, the due publike Liberty, safety and Peace of the Kingdomes.</hi> The glory of God which is first named is the last and ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most end, the rest are but subordinate ends, or rather meanes to procure that last end: Come then, agree for shame, if the glory of God doe not move thee, thou den iest thy selfe to be a <hi>creature,</hi> for thou art not moved with that which was the end of thy creation, the glory of God; if the advancement of Christs Kingdom doth not move thee, thou denyest thy selfe to bee a <hi>Christian;</hi> if the honour and happinesse of the King and his Posterity doth not move thee, thou denyest thy selfe to bee a <hi>Subject;</hi> if publike liberty doth not invite thee, thou art a <hi>slave;</hi> if safety doth not perswade thee, thou art <hi>desperate;</hi> if peace cannot charme thee, thou art <hi>Implacable.</hi> Come then, you that have any <hi>Faith</hi> in God, any <hi>love</hi> to God, any <hi>zeale</hi> for God, any <hi>loyalty</hi> to your King, any <hi>naturall affection</hi> to your Countrey, any <hi>charity</hi> for <hi>Ireland, Scotland,</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:111697:14"/> any <hi>Prudence and Providence</hi> for Posterity, any <hi>sense of Religion,</hi> any beliefe that there is a God, and that there will bee a day of Iudgement, I beseech you, I beseech you, as you will answer it at that day, deale honestly with the Searcher of hearts, and expresse your sincerity, zeale, and constancy, in making, and in keeping this Covenant with the Lord of Hoasts.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="imprimatur">
            <p>Librum hunc cui titulus <hi>(The Second Part of the Un-deceiver)</hi> perlegi, nec quicquam in eo reperio quo minus cum summâ utilitate Imprimatur.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Ia. Cranford.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:111697:14"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>